The learning rate is the most important
学习率是最重要的
hyperparameter.
一个超参数
Even if you apply models that other people built
即使你将他人构建的模型应用于
to your own dataset, you'll find that you'll probably
自己的数据集 你也会发现你可能
have to try a number of different values
需要尝试多个不同的学习率值
for the learning rate to get the model to train properly.
才能使模型正确训练
If you took care to normalize the inputs to your model,
如果你归一化模型的输入
then a good starting point is usually 0.01.
一个好的起始点通常是 0.01
And these are the usual suspects of learning rates.
这些是学习率的通常假设
If you try one and your model doesn't train,
如果你试一个 你的模型并没有正确训练
you can try the others from this list.
你可以试试此列表中其他的
Which of the others should you try?
那么你该试哪个呢？
That depends on the behavior of the training error.
这取决于训练误差的行为
To better understand this, we'll need
要更好地理解这一点 我们需要
to look at the intuition of the learning rate.
来看看学习率的直觉判断
Earlier in the course, we saw that when
在此课程早些时候 我们看到
we use gradient descent to train a neural network model,
当我们使用梯度下降来训练神经网络模型时
the training task boils down to decreasing
训练任务的关键在于尽可能降低
the error value calculated by a loss function
损失函数计算的
as much as we can.
误差值
During a learning step, we do a forward pass through the model,
在学习过程中 我们在模型中进行前向迭代
calculate the loss, then find the gradient.
计算损失 然后获得梯度
Let's assume this simplest case, in which
假设在最简单的情况下
our model has only one weight.
我们的模型只有一个权重
The gradient will tell us which way
梯度将告诉我们向哪个方向
to nudge the current weight so that our predictions become
推动当前权重 以提高我们预测
more accurate.
的准确度
To visualize the dynamics of the learning rate,
为了可视化学习率的动态
let us plot the value of the weight versus the error value
我们绘制一个权重值与获得的误差值
we obtained by using it to calculate
的关系图 使用它来计算
a prediction for a random training data point.
随机训练数据点的预测值
In the perfect case, and if we zoom in
在理想情况下 如果我们放大
to the correct part of the curve,
曲线的正确部分
the relationship of the weights and error values
权重和误差值的关系
look like this idealized u-shape.
看起来就像这个完美的 U 型
Choosing a random weight and calculating the error value
选择一个随机权重并计算误差值
would give us a point like this one on the curve.
会使我们获得曲线上这样一个点
Note that we don't know what the curve looks like when we start.
注意 我们一开始时并不知道曲线是什么样的
The only way to know that is to calculate the error
知道它的唯一方式是计算
at every weight point.
每个权重点的误差
We're only drawing it here to clarify these dynamics.
我们在这里将它画出来只是为了展示它的动态变化
Calculating the gradient would tell us
计算梯度会告诉我们
which direction to go to decrease the error.
朝哪个方向可以降低误差
If we do the calculation correctly,
如果我们的计算是正确的
the gradient will point out which direction
梯度会告诉我们下一步的
to go, meaning whether we should increase or decrease
方向 即增大或减小
the current value of the weight.
权重的当前值
The learning rate is the multiplier
学习率是我们用于
we use to push the weight towards the right direction.
将权重推向正确方向的乘数
Now, if we had made a miraculously correct choice
如果我们奇迹般地做出了正确的
for our learning rate, then we'd land on the best weight
学习率选择 那么只需一个
after only one training step.
训练步长 我们就能到达最佳权重
If the learning rate we chose was smaller
如果我们选择的学习率小于
than the ideal rate, then that's OK.
理想的学习率 没关系
Our model can continue to learn until it finds
我们的模型将继续学习 直到
a good value for the weight.
找到权重的最佳值
So each training step it'll take a step closer until it
每个训练步长 它都会更近一步
lands on that best weight at the end.
直到最终到达最佳权重
If, however, the learning rates had been too little,
但是 如果学习率太小
then our training error would be decreasing, but very slowly.
那么我们的训练误差就会降低 但是非常慢
And we might go through hundreds or thousands of training steps
我们可能经过数千个训练步长
without reaching the best value for our model.
也无法到达模型的最佳值
And it's clear that in cases like this what we need to do
很明显 在这种情况下 我们需要做的
is to increase the learning rate.
是提高学习率
One other case is that if we chose a learning rate that
另一种情况是 如果我们选择一个
is larger than the ideal learning rate,
大于理想学习率的学习率
our updated value would overshoot the ideal weight
更新的值则将越过理想的
value.
权重值
And then on the next update it would
下一次更新时 它会
overshoot it the other way.
在反方向越过最佳值
But it will keep getting closer, and it would probably
但它会越来越靠近 可能最终会
converge to a reasonable value.
收敛到一个合理的值
Where this becomes problematic though is
但是如果我们选择的学习率
when we choose a learning rate that
比理想学习率大很多
is much larger than the ideal rate, more than twice as much.
大两倍以上 这就会产生问题
So in this case, we will see the weights taking
在这种情况下 我们会看到权重采取
a large step that not only overshoots the ideal weight,
较大的步长 它不仅越过理想权值
but it actually gets farther and farther
而且实际上离我们每步获得的
from the best error that we can get at every step.
最佳误差越来越远
A contributor to this divergence is the gradient.
导致这种偏离的因素在于梯度
The gradient does not only contribute a direction but also
梯度不仅指出方向 它还
a value that corresponds to the slope of the line tangent
提供曲线上该点的切线
to the curve at that point.
斜率对应的值
The higher the point is on the curve, the more steep
曲线上的点越高 斜率越大
the slope is, and the larger the value of the gradient is.
梯度的值也就越大
So this makes the problem of the large learning rate even worse.
这会使学习率过大的问题更糟
So if our training error is actually increasing,
所以如果我们的训练误差在增加
we might want to try to decrease the learning rate
不妨试试降低学习率
and see what happens.
看看会发生什么
These are the general cases you'll
这些是你在调整学习率时
come across when tuning your learning rate.
会遇到的普遍情况
But note that this here is a simple example with only one
但是注意这是只有一个参数的
parameter, and an ideal convex error curve.
简单示例 并且是理想情况下的凹形误差曲线
Things are more complicated in the real world,
但现实生活中的情况会复杂得多
I'm sure you've seen.
想必你都见到过
Your models are likely to have hundreds or thousands
你的模型会有成百上千的
of parameters, each with its own error
参数 每个都有自己的误差曲线
curve that changes as the values of the other weights change.
会随着其他权重值的变化而变化
And the learning rate has to shepherd all of them
学习率必须引导所有这些
to the best values that produce the least error.
到达产生的误差最小的最佳值
To make matters even more difficult for us,
更糟糕的是
we don't actually have any guarantees
我们实际上无法保证
that the error curves would be clean u-shapes.
误差曲线会是整洁的 U 形
They might, in fact, be more complex shapes
事实上 它们会成为更复杂的形状
with local minima that the learning algorithm
而且学习算法可能会错误地将局部最小值
can mistake for the best values and converge on.
当做最佳值进行收敛
This figure is obviously an oversimplification.
这个图显然已经简化了很多
Because the curve of three parameters versus the error
因为三个参数与误差值的
value is actually a plane in four-dimensional space,
关系曲线在思维空间中是一个平面
and hard to visualize.
很难可视化
So think of this complexity that these incredible algorithms
想想这些先进的算法
can help us overcome.
帮我们克服了多少复杂性
It's easy to be intimidated by a thousand or a million weights,
数千万的权重很容易让人感到害怕
each with their own error curve that
而且它们都有自己的误差曲线
depends on all the other values, plus each weight having
这些曲线要取决于其他值 而且每个权重
a random starting value, and our diligent learning rate pushing
都有随机的起始值 我们勤快的学习率
them left and right in order to fit our training data
将它们左推右推 以拟合训练数据
and find the best model.
并找到最佳模型
But this is a monster you have slain over and over again
这是你在此纳米学位课程中
in the exercises and projects of this Nanodegree.
一次次不断杀死的怪兽
I just wanted to take a second and reflect
我只想花一秒钟时间 感叹一下
on the incredible power we wield,
这些奇妙的算法赋予我们的
armed with these brilliant algorithms.
这些难以置信的力量
Now that we looked at the intuition of the learning
现在我们已经了解了学习率的
rates, and the indications that the training error gives us
直接判断 以及训练误差
that can help us tune the learning rate,
如何帮助我们调整学习率
let's look at one specific case we
下面我们来看一个在调整学习率时
can often face when tuning the learning rate.
经常会遇到的一个具体情形
Think of the case where we chose a reasonable learning rate.
假设我们选择了一个合理的学习率
It manages to decrease the error, but up to a point,
它可以降低误差 但只能到某一个点
after which it's unable to descend,
在那之后就无法下降了
even though it didn't reach the bottom yet.
尽管它还没到达底部
It would be stuck oscillating between values that still have
它会一直在两个值之间振荡 它们
a better error value than when we started training, but are
优于刚开始训练时的误差差
not the best values possible for the model.
但却不是此模型的最佳值
This scenario is where it's useful to have our training
在这种情形下 让我们的训练算法
algorithm decrease the learning rate throughout the training
降低整个训练过程的学习率
process.
会比较有用
This is a technique called learning rate decay.
此技术叫作学习率衰减
Intuitive ways to do this can be by decreasing the learning
这么做的直观方式是线性
rate linearly.
降低学习率
So say, decrease it by half every 5 epochs,
假设 每 5 个 epoch 减半
like this example here.
就像这里这个示例
You can also decrease the learning rate exponentially.
你也可以按指数方式降低学习率
So for example, we'd multiplied the learning rate
例如 每 8 个 epoch
by 0.1 every 8 epochs, for example.
对学习率乘以 0.1
In addition to simply decreasing the learning rate,
除了直接降低学习率外
there are more clever learning algorithms that
还有一些聪明的学习算法
have an adaptive learning rate.
具有自适应学习率
These algorithms are just the learning rate
这些算法能根据其
based on what the learning algorithm knows
知道的问题以及目前为止看到的数据
about the problem and the data that it's seen so far.
调整学习率
This means not only decreasing the learning rate when needed,
这不仅代表在需要时降低学习率
but also increasing it when it appears to be too low.
还表示在学习率太低时升高它
Below this video, you'll find some instructions
在此视频下面 你会找到关于在 TensorFlow 中
for using an adaptive learning algorithm in TensorFlow.
使用自适应学习算法的一些说明